Jorge Saldivar Galli

Summary

Information Technology Engineer and open-source supporter with experience as a software developer, researcher and teacher assistant.

Interests

Social Impact technology, Democratic Innovation, Collective Intelligence, Open Innovation, Crowdsourcing, Software Engineering, Business Process Management, and Social Network Analysis.

Education

2011 - current

PhD in Information and Communication Technology - ICT Doctoral School, University of Trento, Italy.

2001 - 2007

Bachelor of Science (B.Sc.), Informatics Engineering - Catholic University "Nuestra Señora de la Asunción", Asunción, Paraguay.

Thesis: Improving cooperative and competitive behaviors on visually impaired children.

Awards and Honors

PhD On the Move scholarship for PhD students at the University of Trento, Italy.

FC-UPM-IB scholarship for post-graduated studies at Universidad Politécnica de Madrid.

Golden-medal for best graduated student of 2000 class at San José High-School.

Professional Experience

July 2014 - Now

Visiting Scholar - Center for Information Technology Research in Interest of the Society (CITRIS), School of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science, University of California, Berkeley, California, USA.

Implementation of an application that enables public institutions to stay informed about public opinions and priorities posted on Twitter.

Platform: Web-based.

Technologies: Python, Django, Twitter API.

Repository: https://github.com/joausaga/participa

October 2013 - December 2013

Visiting Researcher - Information Analysis Division Hewlett-Packard Laboratories, Palo Alto, California, USA.

Modeling, designing and implementing analytic tools for large-scale parallel-executed SQL queries.

Platform: Web-based.

Technologies: Javascript, Java.

November 2011 - August 2013

Researcher - BPM4People Project (http://www.bpm4people.org): EU-funded research project.

BPM4People aims at constructing simple, low-cost, high performance methodology, tool suite, and application portfolio that will help B2B organizations harness the flexibility of social business processes design and deployment.

November 2011 - March 2013

Researcher - Ianus Project (https://sites.google.com/site/ssbptester): Trento-province-funded research project.

IANUS aims at business process improvement through a business activity monitoring (BAM) solution that is able to monitor the execution of business processes in highly distributed and loosely-coupled environments.

Development of a spreadsheet-based business process testing tool.

Platform: Web-based.

Technologies: Javascript, Java, Google App Scripts, Google Drive API, MySQL, Activiti.

Repository: http://goo.gl/ZaVlwg

January 2010 - July 2011

Head of Education Technology - NGO Paraguay Educa.

Responsible for the deployment of innovative technologies in schools benefited the project One Laptop per Child.

Development of applications and main-stream patches.

Platform: Sugar Learning Platform

Technologies: Python, PHP, Javascript, MySQL, Git. Repository: http://git.sugarlabs.org/~jasg

March 2008 - December 2008

Head of Technology - One Laptop per Child pilot project

Responsible of the technical aspects needed for deploying the pilot. Mounting servers, setting up XO laptops, developing sugar learning platform applications.

Platform: Sugar Learning Platform

Technologies: Python.

March 2007 - December 2007

Software Developer - Azucarera Iturbe: Sugar Industry

Development, test and maintenance of a business management system.

Platform: Web-based.

Technologies: Ruby on Rails, Javascript.

February 2006 - July 2007

Assistant Professor - Science and Technology School, Catholic University "Nuestra Señora de la Asunción"

Assistant Professor in Programming Languages 1 class of the Informatics Engineering program.

December 1999 - December 1999

 $Software\ Engineer$ - High-School internship at Casa Escauriza I.C.S.A: Cane Industry

Development of a billing system.

Platform: Win 32.

Technologies: Visual Basic.

Technical skills

- Languages: Java, Python, Javascript, R, PHP, SQL, Ruby, C, C++, Bash, $C\sharp$, Visual Basic.
- Frameworks: Ruby on Rails, Yii, ExtJS, Qooxdoo, Drupal, Play, JQuery, Bootstrap, Django.
- API: Twitter, Google Translator, Google Drive.
- Operating Systems: Linux, OS X, Windows.

Open source contributions

Club de Othello: Educational application for visually impaired children (http://activities.sugarlabs.org/en-US/sugar/addon/4286)

Poll: Application for creating polls, collecting votes, and analyzing the community opinions. (http://activities.sugarlabs.org/en-US/sugar/addon/4074)

Labyrinth: Mind-mapping application that supports text, images, and simple drawings. (http://activities.sugarlabs.org/en-US/sugar/addon/4078)

Fingerprint Attendance: Desktop software application that leverages on fingerprints the attendance at events, classes or work. (http://sourceforge.net/projects/attendencesys)

Agora 2.0: Web-based platform for fostering on-line and on-site civic-participation. (http://github.com/joausaga/agora20)

Publications in Refereed Conferences and Journals

- [1] [UNDER-REVIEW] T. Aitamurto, J. Saldivar, J. Salminen. Self-selection in Crowd-sourcing Democracy: A Bug or A Future?. Crowdwork Workshop, ACM Conference on Supporting Groupwork, 2014, Sanibel Island, Florida, USA.
- [2] [UNDER-REVIEW] J. Saldivar, C. Vairetti, C. Rodriguez, F. Daniel, F. Casati, R. Alarcón. Spreadsheet-based testing of business process. Elsevier Information Systems.
- [3] J. Saldivar, C. Parra, C. Rodriguez, L. Cernuzzi, V. D'Andrea. Participa: fostering civic participation for public services innovation. 13th Participatory Design Conference, 2014, Windhoek, Namibia.
- [4] G. Schiavo, M. Milano, J. Saldivar, T. Nasir, M. Zancanaro, G. Convertino. Agora2.0: Enhancing Civic Participation through a Public Display. 6th International Conference on Communities and Technologies, 2013, Munich, Germany.
- [5] J. Saldivar, L. Cernuzzi. Resultados del Club de Othello XO: Una Experiencia de Aprendizaje en Ambiente de Interacción Social. Congress of Technology Support Disabilities (IBERDISCAP), 2010, Ciudad de Mexico, Mexico.
- [6] L. Cernuzzi, J. Saldivar. Club de Othello Xo: Una Experiencia de Aprendizaje en Ambiente de Interacción Social. Congress of Technology Support Disabilities (IBERDISCAP), 2008, Cartegena, Colombia.